<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An account of the late most hahpy rnd [sic] glorious victory, obtained by the imperial army, commanded by His Highness Prince Lewis of Baden, over that of the Turks, commanded by the Grand Vizier : the killing of ten thousand of the Turks on the spot, taking 160 pieces of cannon, all their baggage, &amp;c, with divers other particulars.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75343</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A313A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R173150</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45789123</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45789123</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172437</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75343)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172437)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2630:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An account of the late most hahpy rnd [sic] glorious victory, obtained by the imperial army, commanded by His Highness Prince Lewis of Baden, over that of the Turks, commanded by the Grand Vizier : the killing of ten thousand of the Turks on the spot, taking 160 pieces of cannon, all their baggage, &amp;c, with divers other particulars.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Sanders in St. Jame's-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Licensed, August the 31st. J. Fraiser."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Christ Church (University of Oxford). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ludwig Wilhelm --  I, --  Margrave of Baden, 1655-1707.</term>
               <term>Austro-Turkish War, 1683-1699 --  Sources.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:172437:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 18 -->
            <head>AN ACCOUNT Of the Late Moſt hahpy rnd Glorious Victory, obtained by the Imperial Army, Commanded by His Highneſs Prince <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>Baden,</hi> over that of the <hi>Turks,</hi> Commanded by the <hi>Grand Vizier</hi> The Killing of Ten Thouſand of the <hi>Turks</hi> on the Spot, taking 160 Pieces of Cannon, all their Baggage, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> with Divers other particulars.</head>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>Licenſed,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>
                                 <hi>Auguſt</hi> the 31ſt.</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>J. Fraiſer.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>THE <hi>Ottaman</hi> Army, commanded by the Prime <hi>Vizier,</hi> having not Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed the <hi>Save</hi> into <hi>Bulgaria</hi> (as was lately reported) but, being Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd to a Plain, Four <hi>German</hi> Leagues from <hi>Belgrade,</hi> in the Road that Leads to <hi>Buda,</hi> there deſigning to Intrench themſelves: Of which his Highneſs, Prince Lewis of <hi>Baden,</hi> having timely Notice, Advanc'd towards them with the <hi>Imperial</hi> Army: And on the 19th day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> early in the Morning, Prince <hi>Lewis</hi> At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack'd the Grand <hi>Vizier</hi> in his Camp, before he had time to Intrench himſelf. The Fight laſted for near Five hours, with great Obſtinacy and Reſolution, and much Slaughter; each General being Emulous, to ſhew the utmoſt of his Conduct and Skill, on this great Occaſion: The Succeſs of which, being of the higheſt concern to both Empires.sThe Victory was very diſputable, and even in the Gold-Ballance, for ſeveral Hours, before any Deciſion could be made. But, at laſt, it ſo pleaſed the Omnipoient, and All-wiſe Rector of the Univerſe, by his ſpecial provider <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo far to favour the Juſt and Righteous Cauſe, of his Imperial Majeſty, againſt thoſe Barbarous Infidels, as to turn the ſcale of Battle, by giving the <hi>Turks</hi> a Total De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat, and that with an Horrible Carnage, or Slaughter of the Infidels; who retired with all the Precipitation imaginable, towards the <hi>Save,</hi> leaving behind them all their Artillery, which conſiſted of 160 Cannon, moſt of which were Field-pieces; all their Ammunition, moſt of their ſmall Arms; and, which Crown'd the Work, all their Rich Baggage; there being an Incredible Number of Camels, Mules, and Waggons, laden with riches of an almoſt Ineſtimable Value, (it having been an old Cuſtom, for the <hi>Turks,</hi> to carry the chief of their Treaſure to the Wars.)</p>
            <p>As to the Exact Number of <hi>Turks</hi> 8lain, it is not yet known, in regard when the Expreſs came away, the <hi>Germans</hi> were in purſuit of them over the River <hi>Save</hi> into <hi>Bulgaria;</hi> and that ſo cloſely, that its thought, they had not time to break down any of the Bridges, they had made over the aforeſaid River, after them. Some Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts ſay, 13000, others ſay 10000, Killed on the Spot, and 60000 more in the <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urſuit and drown'd crowding for haſt, in the River <hi>Save;</hi> but the moſt modeſt Account, is Ten Thouſand.</p>
            <p>The loſt on the ſide of the <hi>Imperaliſts</hi> are Computed at about 5000 killed and Wounded; among the latter of which are the Duke <hi>de Aſpremont,</hi> who Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the left Wing, and the Duke <hi>de Arſchat,</hi> The <hi>Imperial</hi> Army, both Officers and <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oldiers, behaving themſelves on this Occaſion, with all the Courage, Reſolution, and Bravery imaginable.</p>
            <p>The next Day (being the 20th.) Prince <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>Baden,</hi> diſpatch Prince <hi>Charles</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o <hi>Lorrain,</hi> (Son to the Duke of Famous Memory) to the Court at <hi>Vienna,</hi> with a Letter to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is <hi>Imperial</hi> Majeſty; to give an Account of this moſt Important Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory; and ikewiſe three other Letters of the ſame Account: One to the King of <hi>Great Briain,</hi> a Second to the Marqueſs <hi>de Caſtinago,</hi> and a Third to the Prince <hi>de Vaudemont.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Ottoman</hi> Army, before the Fight, conſiſted of near 80000 Men; the <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perialiſt,</hi> of 50000. The <hi>French,</hi> a little before this great Action happened gave out in their New Conqueſt, That the <hi>Imperial</hi> Army was Totally Routed by the <hi>Turks:</hi> It's not doubted but that this great, and moſt glorious Victory will ſo far Influence the Council at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> that the Emperor may conclude a Peace, even upon what Terms he pleaſe.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Sanders</hi> in St. <hi>Jame's-ſtreet,</hi> 1691.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
